Guide to the Records of the National Jewish Welfare Board, undated, 1889-1995 (bulk 1917-1990) *I-337
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
- Subgroup I: Governance, 1905-1990 (bulk 1917-1990); 299 linear feet.
  - Series A: Governing Body, 1918-1990 (bulk 1922-1977); 63 linear feet.
    - Subseries 3: Executive Director/Vice President, 1967-1968, 1970-1990; 9 linear feet.
      This subseries documents the administration of JWB from the late 1960s through 1990. The bulk of these documents relate to Sanford Solender, who served as Executive Director from 1960 to 1970. Material on Executive Directors Herbert Millman (1970-1976) and Arthur Rotman (1977-1995) and Presidents Louis Stern (1966-1969) and Morton L. Mandel (1970-1974) is also located here. The files provide information on the JCC movement, both in the USA and abroad. Other issues include civil rights, selective service, JWB administration, Israel, war claims against Germany, JWB's relationship with other Jewish organizations, union and personnel matters, and contemporary issues concerning the Jewish community and JWB. The subseries also contains photographs of Herbert Millman, Morton L. Mandel, and General Westmoreland, Army Chief of Staff. Document types include correspondence, press releases and clippings, meeting minutes, financial statements, architectural drawings, workbooks, and photographs, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials subgroup.
    - Subseries 4: Office of the President, 1918-1964; 21 linear feet.
      This subseries is divided into three subsubseries: 1) Frank L. Weil Files (1918-1957; bulk 1937-1950), 2) Frank L. Weil Award Files (1950-1964), and 3) Irving Edison Files (1942-1956; bulk 1950-1956). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      This subseries consists mainly of the files of Frank Weil, who served as JWB president from 1940 to 1950. Some material relating to Irving Edison, JWB president from 1950 to 1954, can also be found here. As such, the documents provide information as to the activities and preoccupations of JWB's leaders during and immediately after World War II. Of particular note is the material on Jewish veteran affairs and files relating to JWB's efforts during World War II, including JWB's relationships with the Army and Navy, and with the USO. JWB's relationship with other Jewish and non-Jewish organizations is also documented here. (The subseries also includes a small amount of material related to the Frank L. Weil award, which was first given in 1951. The award recognizes distinguished work in JWB's three areas of focus: the JCC field, the Armed Services field, and the advancement of American Jewish culture.) The records contain correspondence, clippings, press releases, sketches, brochures, budget and financial materials, reports, speeches, by-laws and constitutions, histories, manuals, and photographs and recordiographs, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
  - Series B: Fund Raising Services, 1948-1986 (bulk 1950-1983); 51 linear feet.
    This series is divided into four subseries: 1) Fund Raising Division; 2) JWB Associates; 3) Large City Budgeting Conference; and 4) Support and Development Services.
    The Fund Raising Services Department reviewed the financial condition of JWB and expedited communication between the various members of JWB, the Centers, and the National Finance Council.
    - Subseries 1: Fund Raising Division, 1948-1966; 6 linear feet.
      Arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
      The Fund Raising Division functioned as the primary means to raise the funds needed to meet the cost of operating all of JWB divisions. The JWB received monies from various Jewish Welfare funds, Community Councils and, in New York City, from the Greater New York United Jewish Appeal fund. The JCCs and YMHAs around the country and Canada make up the rest of the monies needed to balance the budget. Other activities documented are the Korean War effort of JWB, community visits examining the fund raising campaigns of the Centers, and the meetings of the National Finance Council.
      Types of material include correspondence, pamphlets, newsletters, reports, financial statements, memoranda, articles, speeches, minutes, flyers, rules and regulations, bulletins, news clippings, press releases, policies, plans and procedures, field surveys, and photographs (located in Audio/Visual Subgroup).
    - Subseries 2: JWB Associates, 1967-1984 (bulk 1980-1984); 6 linear feet.
      At the 1956 Biennial a new group called JWB Associates came into being to draw from the larger JWB family. Although construed as a fund raising effort, the objective was to raise awareness in the community of all the functions of JWB, including services rendered to the Armed Forces overseas. JWB Facts says "JWB Associates was established in order to give individual community leaders in all part of the country an opportunity to express concretely their belief in the values of JWB's activities and to actively support its work beyond their regular contribution to their local Jewish federations and welfare funds."1
      The subseries highlights the fund raising and membership campaigns of JWB Associates as well as their role within the communities.
      The kinds of records found are brochures, membership lists, drafts, correspondence, worksheets, requisitions, computer printouts, and photographs (located in Audio-Visual Material Subgroup).
      1 About JWB Associates," JWB Facts, undated, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series B: Fund Raising Services/Subseries 4: Support and Development.
    - Subseries 3: Large City Budgeting Conference, 1982-1983; 1 linear foot.
      The Large City Budgeting Conference is an informal association of Jewish welfare funds that annually engages in analysis and review of national and overseas agency programs and budgets. The records highlight the preparations for the conferences.
      Types of material are financial statements, correspondence, reports, brochures, balance sheets, and agendas.
    - Subseries 4: Support and Development Services, 1950-1986 (bulk 1953-1975); 38 linear feet.
      Administrative Files (1970-1980), Correspondence (1973-1974, 1979), Fair Share Communities Dues and Records (1975-1986), Non-Fair Share Communities (1950-1965, bulk 1960-1965), New York United Jewish Appeal - JWB Dinner (1951-1963), New York City Council Files (1952-1965), Scholarship Material, Harold Dinerman Fund (1976-1977).
      JWB adopted the Fair Share plan in 1960 in order to ensure that each JCC and YMHA gave to JWB a portion of monies in relation to its financial situation. A formula was established to determine the amount give by each Jewish community, ¼ of 1 percent of the annual average of the gross income raised by the local Jewish Federations over a three-year period plus 1.5 percent of the local JCC or YMHA's budget averaged over a three-year period. The Non-fair share communities included Jewish Welfare Fund, United Jewish Appeal, Armed Services Committee, Jewish Community Council, and Jewish Community Chest.
      The Support and Development materials reveal several aspects of JWB's relationship with the various JCCs and YMHAs. In particular are the conflicts between the agencies regarding fund raising, contributions, the fair share program, and the problem that local agencies had in raising money for the JWB within their communities. JWB had to combat the feeling of "What does the JWB do for me?" Also highlighted are the descriptions of services available to the local Jewish communities from the Centers and JWB.
      The Scholarship Material Files describe the fund established after Harold Dinerman's death for graduate students in social work and the people who donated monies to it. For more information on Harold Dinerman please see his biography in the appendix. Types of records included are financial statements, correspondence, forms, contracts, plans and policies, brochures, proposals, news clippings, newsletters, guidelines, programs, studies, reports, drafts, memoranda, budgets, photographs (located in Audio-Visual Material Subgroup), by-laws, applications, minutes, program guides, ledgers cards, membership lists, telegrams, yearbooks, invitation cards, handwritten notes, agendas, workbooks, and obituaries.
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series A: Governing Body/Subseries 1: Annual Meetings; Subgroup I: Governance/Series B: Fund Raising Services/ Subseries 2: JWB Associates.
  - Series C: Central Records Center, undated, 1905-1986 (bulk 1917-1970); 148 linear feet.
    This series is divided into six subseries: 1) Archives and Records; 2) General Files; 3) History Files; 4) Holiday Files; 5) JWB Administrative Files; and 6) National Services.
    The Central Records Center was considered the "memory" of JWB because of the historic material filed within. By the mid-1960's JWB realized that their filing system was in chaos and requested the services of Colonel Seymour Pomrenze. The Colonel had previously been Archivist for the National Archives and an archivist for the US Military. Colonel Pomrenze helped the JWB develop a more efficient records management program in order to control the large amount of paperwork produced every year.
    The Central Records Center obtained copies of most of the documents released by each department within JWB so that the records could be used for reference purposes in the future and to establish institutional memory. Selected documents were eventually transferred to the Archives of JWB and kept permanently until they were given to the American Jewish Historical Society.
    - Subseries 1: Archives and Records, 1963-1986; 1 linear foot.
      Files of Colonel Pomrenze. Arranged alphabetically.
      The subseries describes the process by which JWB's records were organized before and after 1967 and reviews the functions and relationships between the various departments of JWB.
      Types of records found are memoranda, correspondence, forms, guides, directories, organizational charts, reports, surveys, and agendas.
    - Subseries 2: General Files, undated, 1918-1981 (bulk 1938-1975); 46 linear feet.
      The General files subseries is comprised of files too small to be maintained in a separated series of records. Included are materials dealing with such topics as refugees, immigration, obituaries, war-related records, and the founding of Israel.
      Of special interest are the documents relating to the synagogue-center relationship. In the journal articles, studies, theses, and speeches can be found an analysis of the similarities and differences between synagogue centers and JCCs. Also included is a file documenting Congregation Brothers of Israel's struggle to preserve their historic synagogue from destruction in Long Branch, NJ.
      Kinds of records included are correspondence, pamphlets, news clippings, reports, brochures, photographs (located in Audio-Visual Material Subgroup), memoranda, plays and scripts, press releases, articles, telegrams, publications, newspapers, speeches, newsletters, constitutions, by-laws, music, and policies.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous box 1 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to the General Files and consists of miscellaneous subject files.
    - Subseries 3: History Files, 1915-1980 (bulk 1917-1970); 7 linear feet.
      Miscellaneous alphabetical files A-P, applications for affiliation, chaplains, by-laws and constitutions, Rabbi Lee Levinger, World War I, World War II, History of YMHA Movement. Arranged alphabetically.
      The subseries consists of historical material regarding JWB, the YMHA movement, chaplains, WWI, and applications from organizations seeking affiliation. The records of the YMHA movement include correspondence, working papers, and manuscript material of Benjamin Rabinowitz who authored The Young Men's Hebrew Associations, 1854-1913.
      Types of materials found are memoranda, brochures, articles, reports, minutes, invitations, holiday postcards, speeches, pamphlets, applications, forms, newspaper clippings, by-laws, constitutions, correspondence, maps (located in Oversized Materials Subgroup), books, WWI JWB Insignia, WWI coin board, WWI JWB inscribed wallet, V-Mail, surveys and studies, programs, and photographs (located in Audio/Visual Subgroup)
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series A: Governing Body/Subseries 1: Annual Meetings; Subgroup III: Veterans Affairs/Series B: CJC/Chaplains; Subgroup IV: Affiliated Organizations/Series A: National Affiliated Organizations - Series D: YMHA.
      Restrictions: Some folders are restricted due to the fragility of their contents.
    - Subseries 4: Holiday Files, 1905-1972 (bulk 1935-1960); 7 linear feet.
      Arranged alphabetically.
      The subseries contains material related to Chanukah, the High Holy Days, Passover, Purim, Shavuot, Succoth, U.S. National Holidays, and the Sabbath. These documents reflect the program material distributed by JWB to the departments, Centers and servicemen.
      Types of records included are correspondence, bulletins, manuals, postcards, musical scores, memoranda, plays, articles, newspapers clippings, reports, press releases, pamphlets, cards, and radio transcripts.
      Related Materials: Subgroup III: Veterans' Affairs.
    - Subseries 5: JWB Administrative Files, 1919-1986 (bulk 1940-1969); 78 linear feet.
      Address and Articles, Board of Directors, Budget Material, Centennial Celebration, Circular Letters, Committees, Confidential Subject Files (not restricted), General Files, Institutes, Master Set of JWB Documents, Organizational Files, Other - History Articles, Policies, Refugee Problems. Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
      The JWB Administrative Files subseries recounts the development and function of JWB, JCCs, and the Armed Forces Division, as well as the management and administration of the JWB offices including staffing needs, records management, and retirement plans. The Centennial Celebration material documents JWB's activities during the 100th anniversary of the Baltimore YMHA, the first in America. The General Files material consists of records mainly from the offices of Executive Vice President, Assistant Executive Director, and other key JWB officials. Louis Kraft is prevalent throughout the materials. The Master Set of Documents is made of up records produced by each office or department of the JWB. This material highlights membership trends, budgeting trends, statistics, changes and development in American Jewry, and the Soviet-Jewish resettlement. Also included are documents relating to Oscar Janowsky's 1946 Study Commission. For more information on Louis Kraft please see his biography in the appendix.
      Types of documents found are addresses, speeches, articles, correspondence, newspaper clippings, reports, financial statements, agendas, by-laws, studies, memoranda, guides, proposals, circular letters, press releases, minutes, ledgers, pamphlets, programs, manuals, photographs (located in Audio-Visual Material Subgroup), radio and TV transcripts, telegrams, resolutions, agreements, plans, rules and regulations, yearbooks, proceedings, directories, flyers, histories, charts, and policies.
      Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series A: Governing Body/Subseries 3: Executive Director, Vice President - Subseries 4: Associate Executive Director, Vice President; Subgroup II: JCC/Series G: Files and Reports/Subseries 1: Jewish Center Division.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous Boxes 2 and 3 are located at end of entire collection. The material relates to the Circular Letters, General Files, and Policies.
    - Subseries 6: National Services, undated, 1934-1969 (bulk 1944-1968); 9 linear feet.
      This subseries has been divided into two categories: Director's Subject Files and Music Council Playwriting Contest.
      According to the JWB "the objective of the National Services Department is to provide stimulation, guidance, and resources to local Jewish Community Centers in serving the needs and interests of Center members, members of the armed forces and veteran's hospitals, and in strengthening the Jewish cultural and communal program in local communities."2 The Music Council's playwriting contest was held for the Golden Jubilee of JWB in 1967. Anyone could enter a one-act play based on a Jewish theme. The contest started in late 1966 and the winners were announced in October 1967.
      The subseries highlights the department's concentration on the activities of Centers, the cultural arts, personnel training, and important social issues facing American Jews such as civil rights and one-parent families.
      Types of records found are pamphlets, reports, memoranda, studies, bibliographies, indices, proceedings, minutes, constitutions, by-laws, articles, photographs (located in Audio-Visual Material Subgroup), speeches, newsletters, newspaper clippings, proposals, polices, guides, directories, histories, forms, brochures, telegrams, correspondence, and plays.
      2 JWB National Services Emphases for 1966-1967, April 18, 1966, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
      Related Materials: Subgroup II: JCC/Series A: Program Services and Series E: Jewish Education Programs.
      Note: JWB Miscellaneous boxes 3 and 4 are located at end of entire collection. The material consists of the Music Council Playwriting Contest.
  - Series D: Conventions and Committees, 1926-1986 (bulk 1946-1986); 37 linear feet.
    JWB Biennial Conventions (1943-1986), Committee on Admissions (1926-1949), Conference on Jewish Cultural Arts (1974-1976), Conference on Membership Problems (1949-1951), Special Committee to Study Board of Directors (1953), Special Convention for Center Leaders (1949-1985, with gaps), Study Committee (1947-1969), Assorted Meetings (1982-1985), Commission on Maximizing Jewish Educational Effectiveness (1983), and Conference of Jewish Communal Service (1983-1984). Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    This series consists primarily of materials relating to the planning and programming of JWB Biennial Conventions. The Biennial Convention consisted of forums and workshops on a variety of topics, covering all aspects of JCC operations. (The first Biennial was conducted in 1950; prior to that, JWB had held annual meetings.) These documents provide a look at JWB's and the JCCs' principal concerns over the years. Included here are the files of several JWB staff members involved in planning and carrying out Biennials. Individuals whose files are collected here include Harry B. Schatz, Harold Arian, Arthur Brodkin, Sherwood Epstein, and Mitchell Jaffe. (For additional information on these individuals, please see the biographical material in the appendix.) Of particular note are an address by President Truman, and letters from various senators and congressmen, including Senators John Fitzgerald Kennedy and Lyndon Baines Johnson. Also included is a small amount of material on other conferences and committees, such as the Committee on Admissions, which invited JCCs, Synagogues, and Hebrew centers to become members of JWB, and the Study Committee, which sought to increase the effectiveness of JWB and the Jewish community it serves. Included are reports, programs, correspondence, agendas, statistics, brochures, lists, questionnaires, minutes, clippings, photographs and audiotapes, which are located in the Audio-Visual Materials Subgroup.
    Related Materials: Subgroup I: Governance/Series A: Governing Body/Annual Meeting, and Affiliated Organizations/World Federations of YM & YWHA and JCCs; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series B: Field Services/Subseries 1: Community Services. Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series C: Public Relations/Subseries 2: Public Information Services: Communications Awards; Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers/Series E: Jewish Education Programs/Subseries 2: Commission on Maximizing Jewish Educational Effectiveness. In addition, further material on the Biennial can be found throughout the collection.
    Note: JWB Miscellaneous Box 5 is located at end of entire collection. The material relates to Conference of Jewish Communal Service, Assorted Meetings, and Commission on Maximizing Jewish Educational Effectiveness.
  - Series E: JWB Survey, 1947-1953; 2 linear feet.
    The JWB survey dealt with three main concerns: 1) the purpose and programs of centers; 2) the nature of the center movement and of JWB as its national body; 3) the relationship of centers and JWB to Jewish and general communities.3
    3 Solender, Sanford, The Center and You, The Post-JWB Survey Decade, undated, I-337 NJWB, American Jewish Historical Society.
    - Subseries 1: Oscar Janowsky Working Papers, 1947-1953; 2 linear feet.
      This series contains the papers of Oscar Janowsky, who developed the JWB survey. Janowsky's files document the process by which the survey was created, and actions taken to implement survey recommendations. Also included is correspondence with Louis Kraft (JWB Vice President/Executive Director, 1939-1947) regarding the survey. Materials include correspondence, minutes, reports, studies, press releases and clippings, brochures, proposals, and resolutions.
      Related Materials: AJHS collection I-180, JWB Army-Navy Division, which includes 23 boxes of Janowsky's working papers.
- Subgroup II: Jewish Community Centers, undated, 1904-1995 (bulk 1920-1980); 919 linear feet.
  Primarily arranged alphabetically. This subgroup is arranged into seven series as follows: Series A: Program Services; Series B: Field Services; Series C: Public Relations; Series D: Personnel Recruitment and Training; Series E: Jewish Education Programs; Series F: Administrative and Management Services and Series G: Files and Reports.
  This subgroup documents how the Jewish Community Centers functioned as part of JWB and as individual facilities. JWB offered many services to the Centers, and in return the Centers helped support JWB's mission to enrich the Jewish Community throughout the United States and the World.
  - Series A: Program Services, 1904-1989 (bulk 1930-1980); 234.46 linear feet.
    This series is divided into fourteen subseries as follows: 1) Camping Services; 2) Florence Heller Research Center; 3) Health and Physical Education; 4) Jewish Book Council; 5) Jewish Media Service; 6) Jewish Music Council; 7) Lecture Bureau; 8) Nursery School; 9) Older Adults; 10) Program Development and Research Services; 11) Publications; 12) Statistics and Research Development; 13) Vocational Guidance; and 14) Youth Programming.
    This series provides a look at the various programs that JWB helped coordinate for itself, the centers, and the affiliated organizations around the world. A successful social organization is only as strong as its curriculum. JWB understood this, and worked towards the goal of providing the most up-to-date and informative programming it could.
    - Subseries 1: Camping Services, 1941-1988; 38 linear feet.
      Arthur Brodkin (1941-1976), Alfred Dobrof (1973-1975), Sherwood Epstein (1971-1979), General files (1948-1981, bulk 1970-1976), Roslyn Kriegsfeld (1956-1976), Leonard Rubin (1957-1988), Shlichim Program (1969-1970). Arranged alphabetically, except Alfred Dobrof material, which is chronological, then alphabetical.